Ralph Coolidge Henry Papers
Ralph Coolidge Henry Papers
1940-1952
Henry, Ralph Coolidge
18 linear ft.
Correspondence, subject files and architectural plans for Henry projects and clients, such as Colby Junior College, Pine Manor, Boston, Philips Andover Academy, and the Nevada St. School in Newton, Massachusetts. Henry worked with landscape architect Guy Lowell.
2664850
Biographical History
Ralph Coolidge Henry was an American architect who worked primarily in New England. Henry worked with landscape architect Guy Lowell.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ralph Coolidge Henry Papers consist of correspondence, subject files and architectural plans for Henry projects and clients, such as Colby Junior College, Pine Manor, Boston, Philips Andover Academy, and the Nevada St. School in Newton, Massachusetts.
Arrangement of the Collection
Collection remains in original order; inventory is a simple box list supplemented by an alphabetical list of projects created by staff.
Related Material
has the collections of a number of notable architects. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Architects; Henry, Ralph Coolidge -- Archives.; Architectural contracts.; Architecture -- Specifications.; Architecture -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Architectural drawing -- United States -- 20th century.; Dwellings -- Design and construction.; Housing -- Design and construction.; Schools -- Design and construction.; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Contracts.; Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Photographs.; Sketches.; Tracings.; Architects.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Office of Price Administration (Box 1)
  - Office of Price Administration (Box 1)
  - Personal
    - Pangburn Report, Henry, R.C. (Box 1)
    - 200 Church Street, Henry, R.C. (Box 1)
  - New England Trust Company (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clipping on Traffic Problems (Box 1)
  - Newton National Bank (Box 1)
  - Framing (Pencil Drawing and Measurements) (Box 1)
  - Fiberglass (Box 1)
  - Aerial Photos, New Hampshire, November 1946 (Box 1)
  - G.I. Data (Box 1)
  - M.I.T. (Massachusetts Institute of Technology, "Levenburg" Model Tenement, Lower East Side, New York City (Reports), 1938 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence (Business) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Outgoing) (Box 1)
  - Cost Data (Box 1)
  - Current (Box 1)
  - Colby Junior College
    - Heating Ventilation and Air Conditioners (Box 1)
    - Wheeler. W.K. **** School Equipment (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, Drawings, Pamphlets, Clippings (Box 2)
    - Specs (Box 2)
    - H. Leslie Sawyer (Box 2)
    - Various Buildings (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Garage Dormitory Bids and Tabulation (Box 2)
  - Concrete and Monolithic Construction (Box 2)
  - Bradford, Robert F. (Box 2)
  - Traffic, Boston (see also Harvey, C.W.), 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Swimming Pool, Babson Institute (Box 2)
  - Addresses, Profession List (Box 2)
  - Architects (Box 2)
  - Architect's Fees (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - 1942-1945 (Box 2)
    - 1946 (Box 2)
    - Small Drawings (Box 2)
    - 1952 (Box 3)
    - Programs (Church, Drama, Art) (Box 3)
    - 1947 (Box 3)
  - Rawson, George E. (Box 3)
  - Recreation (Box 3)
  - Photos, Aerials (St. Paul, Minnesota), 1946 October (Box 3)
  - Room of the Month Ideas, American Standard (Box 3)
  - State Service Build Commission, St. Paul Minnesota, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Specification for Alteration, 277 Mass. Ave, Cambridge, Mass. (Box 3)
  - Specification for Plumbing, Library, Babson Park Mass. (Box 3)
  - Specification, fragments undated (Box 3)
  - Mt. Auburn Cemetery, Cambridge, Mass., Addenda to General Specs, Alteration to Story Chapel (Box 3)
  - Shawmut Bank (Box 4)
  - Spear, Abbott (Box 4)
  - Shurbert, Fred (Box 4)
  - Specification (Box 4)
  - Checking List (Box 4)
  - Specification Notes
    - 8. Stone Work (Box 4)
    - 25. Asphalt Tile (Box 4)
    - 29 Painting (Box 4)
  - Memorabilia
    - Large Post Cards, White Mountain, N.H. (Box 4)
  - U.S. Trust Company (Box 4)
  - Waterproofing (Box 4)
  - Thayer, William G. Jr. (Box 4)
    See also United Nations.
  - Time Schedules (Box 4)
  - United Nations (Box 4)
  - Walton's Restaurant, School St., Boston, Mass. (Box 4)
  - Walton's, Tony Malfa's Notes (Box 4)
  - Walton, Paul (Box 4)
  - Nazarene College, Dr. Samuel Young (Box 4)
  - War Vets Memorial, news clippings (Box 5)
  - Receipts, Financial Accounts (Box 5)
  - Statements of Financial Condition (Box 5)
  - Professional Statements (Box 5)
  - Pine Manor, Port of Boston (Box 5)
  - Office, 1946 (Box 5)
  - Office, 1947 (Box 5)
  - Office Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous Subject Material, 1952; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Photographs, New York County Courthouse Foley Square, New York, New York; architect Guy Lowell (Box 5)
  - Photographs, Grosse Pointe Yacht Club, Grosse Pointe, Mich.; architects Lowell and/or Henry (Box 5)
  - Photographs, Plant, Morton, F., Groton, Conn.; architects Guy Lowell & R.C. Henry (Box 5)
  - Photographs, Nevada Street School, Newtonville, Mass.; architects Ralph Coolidge Henry, 1934-1935 (Box 5)
  - Photographs, Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Magazine clippings (Box 5)
  - Architect contract (Box 6)
  - Massachusetts State Association of Architects (Box 6)
  - Forms, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Daily Planner/ Calendar, 1946; 1947; 3 items (Box 6)
  - Personal Notebook, 1946 (Box 6)
- Books and Pamphlets
  - Bethlehem Manual of Steel Construction / Bethlehem Steel Co., Bethlehem, Pa., 1934 (Box 7)
  - War Emergency Powers of Massachusetts / Emergency Public Works Commission, The Commonwealth of Massachusetts, January, 1945 (Box 7)
  - Specifications for the Alteration to Munro Hall / Eastern Nazarene College, Wallaston Park Quincy, Mass (Box 7)
  - Preliminary Data, Inscriptions and Tests - Sect. 1-0 / Stevens Master Specifications for Architects and Builders, Stevens, Frank B. Jr., 1932 (Box 7)
  - Construction of the Court House Invitation to Bid, Form of Bid, Contract and Specification and Form of Bond / The Court House Board, New York County, May 1917 (Box 7)
  - Specifications for the Construction of the U.S.H.A.-Aided Housing Project MASS 2-2 in the South Boston District of the City of Boston, Massachusetts, Henry and Richmond, architects / Boston Housing Authority, Sept 25, 1939 (Box 8)
  - Some Statues of Boston (463)/ Forbes, Allan and Eastman, Ralph M., State Street Trust Co., 1946 (Box 8)
  - Catalogue of the Christian Science Publishing Society / The Christian Science Publishing Society, Feb. 1952 (Box 8)
  - Alderman (Mayor) City of Newton / Mayor, Aldermen and Departments and Boards, 1944-1945 (Box 8)
  - Lakes Region of New Hampshire / The Lakes Region Association, Laconia, N.H., undated (Box 8)
  - Year Book and By-Laws of the Parish of the Grace Church in the City of Newton, Diocese of Massachusetts -458 / Grace Church, Newton 1935-1936, undated (Box 8)
  - Catalogue of Works on Christian Science / Eddy, Mary Baker (Box 9)
  - Babson Park, Babson Institute of Business Administration, 1952-1953 (Box 9)
  - Some Examples from the Work of the Office of R. Clipston Sturgis, Architect 120 Boylston Street, Boston, Mass. (Box 9)
  - Solar Ephemeris and Polaris Tables / C.L. Berger & Sons, Inc., Roxbury, Boston, Mass., 1950 (Box 9)
  - Course catalog, Boston University Evening Division / Boston Real Estate Board and the Massachusetts Board of Real Estate Appraisers, August 1951 (Box 9)
  - Minimum Construction Requirements for New Dwellings Located in State of New Hampshire / Federal Housing Administration Concord, N.H., May 15, 1938 (Box 9)
  - The Bay State Builder / Associated General Contractors of Massachusetts, September, 1947 (Box 9)
  - Presidents' Report: The War Record of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology - 461, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1945 (Box 9)
  - Laws Relating to the Erection, Alteration, Inspection and use of Buildings / Dept. of Public Safety, The Commonwealth of Massachusetts, 2 copies (Box 9)
  - Board of Registration of Architects / Commonwealth of Massachusetts, 1943; 1946 (Box 9)
  - The New Hampshire Historical Society, Concord, New Hampshire, 1940 (Box 9)
  - "News"
  - Eastman Kodak Company, Architectural Record, Sept. 1945; Feb. 1946 (Box 9)
  - Bay State Architect, Feb. 1952 (Box 9)
  - A Guide Trip Through the Minnesota State Capitol (Box 9)
- Specifications
  - Henry and Richmond
    - Plumbing Specifications for a House for Mrs. Randolph Frothingham, Brookline, Mass (Box 9)
    - Heating Specifications, Frothingham House (Box 9)
  - Henry & Richmond Architexts; Barber Company Engineers
    - Specification for Heating and Ventilating Apparatus for Bank and Building 99-101 Newbury Street Boston, MA for New England Trust Company (Box 9)
  - Henry & Richmond
    - Electric Specifications for the Back Bay Branch Offices of the New England Trust Company at Nos. 99-101 Newbury Street, Boston MA, 2 copies (Box 9)
    - City of Newton, MA Public Buildings Dept. Invitation to Contractors for Bids for the Erection of a New Schoolhouse, etc, 2 copies (Box 9)
  - Henry, Ralph Coolidge
    - Specifications for a House for Mrs. Warren S. Kilburn at W. Newton, MA (Box 9)
  - Schwamb, Theodore
    - Specification for Erection and Completion of "Thesco" Homes from the Drawings and Details (Box 9)
  - Ralph Coolidge Henry
    - Specification for Benvenue Street Residence for Tenacre at Wellesley, Massachusetts (Box 9)
    - Fragments of table of Table of Contents [no building name] (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous
  - Map, Port of Boston, Boston, Mass., undated (Box 9)
- Index by project
  Albiani Building, Massachusetts Ave. and Pearl St. Cambridge, MA; Architect: Henry
  1 drawing
  13 photos of drawings
  Ahlers Association Club House, Andover MA; Architect: Lowell (1921)
  38 tracings and blueprints
  Babson Institute, Library Building; Architect: G. Marlowe (1924, 1936)
  7 linens
  22 blueprints
  1 tracing
  Babson Institute, Map Room (1940)
  7 blueprints
  4 linens
  Babson Institute, Swimming Pool Building; Architect: Henry (1947)
  1 blueprint
  3 tracings
  Baker, William B. Esq. house, West Newton, MA; Architect: Henry and Richmond
  19 tracings
  Boston Housing Authority, housing project, Charlestown, MA; Architect: John M. Gray (1939)
  3 blueprints
  Boston Housing Authority, housing project, South Boston, MA
  26 blueprints
  24 linens
  42 tracings
  54 "Daily Report" sketches
  10 photos of blueprints
  1 sketch
  Bullock, Hugh, house Andover MA; Architect: Lowell (1924)
  22 tracings
  Chilton Club, Boston, MA
  72 blueprints
  Coe, W.R., alterations of barn planting fields, Long Island, NY; Architect: Lowell (1917)
  2 blueprints, poor condition
  Colby Junior College, dorms and garage, New London, NH; Architect: Henry (1947)
  3 layout sketches
  1 negative of layout sketch
  69 blueprints
  21 linens
  5 tracings
  11 photo Reproductions of sketches
  Conant, H.N., house and garden plans, Dedham, MA; Architect: Henry in association with William G. Thayer (1947)
  15 tracings and blueprints
  Crowninshield, Francis B., Marblehead, MA; Architect: Lowell
  29 blueprints
  6 tracings
  14 linens
  Dana Hall School, Pine Manor and Westlea Hall Wellesley, MA; Architect: Lowell and Henry
  83 blueprints
  17 linens
  66 tracings
  Dana Hall School, Play House Wellesley, MA
  48 blueprints
  1 linen
  Eastern Nazarene College, Munro Hall Wollaston, MA; Architect: Henry and Richmond
  2 blueprints
  Eliot Congregational Church, Newton, MA; Architect: Henry and Richmond (1941)
  11 blueprints
  5 photos of blueprints
  11 tracings
  Far Horizon, house and garden
  Frothingham, Ralph, Brookline, MA; Architect: Henry and Richmond (1959)
  33 blueprints
  7 tracings
  5 linens
  Grace Church, Reredos Newton, MA; Architect: Henry (1935)
  Grosse Pointe Yacht Club, Grosse Pointe Shores, MI; Architect: Henry and Richmond
  Roll 1: 52 blueprints
  Roll 2: 37 blueprints
  Henry, Richard Esq., house, Wellesley, MA; Architect: Henry
  2 linens
  HUB Motor Car Co. (George Kulassian, owner), 1283 Washington St., Boston, MA
  Jewell, Theodore E. Esq., house Newton, MA; Architect: Henry
  Kennedy, Mrs. William J., Brookline, MA
  23 blueprints
  7 sketches
  Mantles, misc.; Architect: Henry and Lowell
  26 linens
  Martin, Gustav, garage, Waban, MA; Architect: Henry (1921)
  8 tracings
  Massachusetts School of Art; Architect: Henry and Richmond
  Roll 1: 12 blueprints of heating and vents, plumbing, and electrical
  Roll 2: 25 tracings and blueprints, Misc.
  Roll 3: 30+ misc. blueprints, tracings, linens; poor condition
  McLanathan, Frank W., house and gardens, Andover, MA; Architect: Lowell (1924)
  16 linens
  5 blueprints
  9 tracings
  Mid-Manhattan Engineering Corp., House B; Architect: Richmond
  3 linens
  Misc. pictorial
  Watercolors of light fixtures; sketch of Back Bay Station, Boston MA; John W. Weeks Junior High School; more
  Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, MA; Architect: Henry and Richmond (1946)
  Nevada Street School, Newton, MA; Architect: Henry (1934)
  55 linens
  New England Trust Co. branch offices, Newberry Street, Boston, MA
  22 linens
  12 small blueprints of furniture
  Oak Hill Trust, house, Newton MA, Richmond
  6 linens
  Old Harbor Village, housing project; Architect: Henry and Richmond (1937)
  Phillips Andover Academy, Andover Memorial Tower; Architect: Lowell (1922)
  43 tracings
  Phillips Andover Academy, Samuel F. B. Morse Hall; Architect: Lowell (1927)
  Roll 1: 58 blueprints
  Roll 2: 19 linens and 32 tracings
  Roll 3: 8 linens, 83 tracings, 5 blueprints
  Piping Rock Club, Locust Valley, Long Island, NY; Architect: Lowell
  Plant, Morton F., garden, Groton, CT; Architect: Lowell (1915)
  8 drawings
  26 reproductions of negatives and sketches
  Red Hook, houses Brooklyn, NY
  Sargent, Miss Alice, alterations to "Holm Lea," Brooklyn, NY
  56 tracings
  1 Letter
  Sargent Estate, Brookline, MA; Architect: Henry and Richmond
  Roll 1: "House C" 7 blueprints, 16 tracings
  Roll 2: "House H" 8 linens, 5 blueprints, 30 tracings
  Roll 3: "General" 30 tracings, 11 blueprints, 1 moldy linen
  Scottish Rite Temple, Valley of Boston, MA; Architect: Lawson W. Oakes (1947)
  Sewage Pumping Station, Wakefield, MA; Architect: Lowell (1926)
  South Side Junior High School, Newton, MA; Architect: Henry and Richmond (1930)
  Roll 1: 17 blueprints
  Roll 2: 24 linens and 1 tracing
  Roll 3: 23 blueprints
  State Normal School, dormitory and refectory, Framingham, MA; Architect: Lowell (1914)
  38 linens
  6 tracings (many in poor condition)
  State Normal School, power plant, Bridgewater, MA; Architect: Henry and Richmond (1927)
  18 linens
  18 blueprints
  Sullivan, J.H., house, Brighton, MA; Architect: Henry (1935)
  Thesco House
  12 blueprints
  Troglon, Lincoln, MA
  Unidentified house/cabin (1941)
  Veterans Service Building, Minnesota Competition
  5 drawings
  Walton Lunch Co., School Street, Boston, MA
  9 blueprints
  12 tracings
  4 sketches
  Washington Memorial, Fall River, MA; Architect: Henry and Richmond, with sculptor Frederick Wallen